Register of the Bertram David Wolfe papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1914-1976 (Boxes 16-54)
  - "Towards Leninism," Workers Monthly, 1927 January; Printed copy (Folder 23: 8)
  - "A Program for the Period of Prosperity," and review of Nikolai Bukharin, The Economic Theory of the Leisure Class, Communist, 1927 July-August; Printed copy (Folder 23: 9)
  - Report from the Soviet Union to the Central Executive Committee, Communist Party, U.S.A., 1928?; Typescript (Folder 23: 10)
  - Revolution in Latin America, pamphlet, 1928; Printed copy (Folder 23: 11)
  - The Trotsky Opposition: Its Significance for Americ Workers, pamphlet, 1928; Printed copy (Folder 23: 12)
  - "America Discusses the Opposition," Communist, 1928 January; Printed copy (Folder 23: 13)
  - "Atheism and Evolution," Communist, 1928 March; Printed copy (Folder 23: 14)
  - "Is the VI Congress Being Revised?," Revolutionary Age, 1929 November 1; Printed copy (Folder 23: 15)
  - "Economics of Present Day Capitalism," lecture series New Workers School, New York, 1930s; Mimeographed syllabus (Folder 23: 16)
  - "The Law of Revolution: A Critical Study of the Central Question of Marxist Strategy," lecture series New Workers School, New York?, 1930s; Handwritten, typewritten and mimeographed notes (Folder 23: 17)
  - Lectures on philosophy, New Workers School, New York, 1930s; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 23: 18)
  - "Marxian Economics," lecture series, New Workers School, New York, 1930s; Mimeographed syllabus (Folder 23: 19)
  - "The Nature of Capitalist Crisis," lecture series, New Workers School, New York, 1930s; Mimeographed syllabus (Folder 23: 20)
  - "The Question of Tone,", 1930s; Typescript (Folder 23: 21)
  - Review of Lenin in 1918 (motion picture), 1930s; Typescript (Folder 23: 22)
  - "Rivera and the Critics,", 1930s (Folder 23: 23)
    Typescript and correspondence.
  - Notes and fragments of writings on the Spanish Civil War, 1930s; Holograph and typescript (Folder 23: 24)
  - Speech on Soviet purge trials, 1930s; Typewritten notes (Folder 23: 25)
  - "The Balance Sheet of Behaviorism," Virginia Quarterly Review, 1930 October; Printed copy (Folder 24: 1)
  - "The Next War," series of articles, Revolutionary Age, 1930 May 1 - 1931 May 1; Printed and handwritten copies (incomplete) (Folder 24: 2-3)
  - Lectures on dialectical materialism, New Workers School, New York, 1931-1932; Handwritten, typewritten and mimeographed notes (Folder 24: 4-5)
  - "Does Labor Need a God?," debate with Reverend Edmund B. Chaffee, 1932 January 23; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 24: 6)
  - Letter to the editor, Nation, 1932 April 22; Typescript (Folder 24: 7)
  - "Building a Communist Party in the U.S.A.," Revolutionary Age?, 1932 October 15; Typewritten and printed copy (Folder 24: 8)
  - Lectures on Marxian economics, New Workers School, New York, 1932-1933; Handwritten notes (Folder 24: 9-10)
  - "The Philosophy of Marxism: Dialectical Materialism," lecture, New Workers School, New York, 1933; Mimeographed syllabus (Folder 24: 11)
  - What Is the Communist Opposition?, pamphlet, 1933; Printed copy (Folder 24: 12)
  - "The Mass as Hero," Modern Monthly, 1933 March; Printed copy (Folder 24: 13)
  - "Zionism, Garveyism, Communism," lecture, 1933 October 14; Handwritten notes (Folder 24: 14)
  - Marx and America, pamphlet, 1934; Printed copy (Folder 25: 1)
  - Portrait of America (with Diego Rivera) (1934)
    - Introduction (Folder 25: 2)
    - Reviews, Printed copies. (Folder 25: 3-4)
  - Things We Want to Know, pamphlet, 1934; Printed copy (Folder 25: 5)
  - "Diego Rivera on Trial," Modern Monthly, 1934 July; Printed copy (Folder 25: 6)
  - Lectures on Marxian economics, New Workers School, New York, 1934-1935; Handwritten notes and mimeographed syllabus (Folder 25: 7)
  - "What Will I Do When America Goes to War?," symposium (with others), Modern Monthly, 1935 September; Printed copy (Folder 25: 8)
  - "Marxism and the Negro," Race, 1935-1936 Winter; Printed copy (Folder 25: 9)
  - Letter to the editor, Nation, 1936 April 1; Printed copy (Folder 25: 10)
  - "Present Economic and Political Situation in Mexico,", 1936 May 5; Typescript (Folder 25: 11)
  - Untitled report on Mexico, 1936 May 14; Typescript (Folder 25: 12)
  - Civil War in Spain, pamphlet, 1937; Printed copy (Folder 25: 13)
  - Introduction to 'Lambda,' The Truth about the Barcelona Events, pamphlet, 1937; Printed copy (Folder 25: 14)
  - Portrait of Mexico (with Diego Rivera) (1937)
    - Introduction, Typescript. (Box-folder 25: 15)
    - Reviews
      - General, Printed copies. (Folder 25: 16)
      - Beals, Carleton (Folder 25: 17)
        Typescript with correspondence.
      - Poore, Charles, New York Times, 1937 (Folder 25: 18)
        Printed copy (April 11), with printed copy of reply by Bertram D. Wolfe (June 6).
      - Schapiro, Meyer (Folder 25: 19)
        Typescript with correspondence and reply by Bertram D. Wolfe.
  - "Background of Spain's Civil War," Marxist Quarterly, 1937 October-December; Printed copy (Folder 25: 20)
  - "Meaning of Soviet Purge," speech, 1937 October 30; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 25: 21)
  - "Civil War in Spain: What's Ahead," speech, 1937 December 22; Typewritten notes (Folder 25: 22)
  - "The Second World War Is Here," Workers Age, 1938?; Printed copy (Folder 25: 23)
  - Speech on Soviet purge trials, 1938? March 9; Typescript (Folder 25: 24)
  - Speech on Spanish Civil War, 1938 March 12; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 25: 25)
  - "Since Lenin Died: Origin and Development of the Stalinist Regime," lecture, 1938 April; Typewritten notes (Folder 25: 26)
  - "Frida Kahlo de Rivera" (in Spanish), Letras de Mexico, 1938 November; Printed copy (Folder 25: 27)
  - "Records of the Moscow Trials," lecture, 1938 November 16; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 25: 28)
  - "History Happens to All," Workers Age, 1938 December 17; Printed copy (Folder 25: 29)
  - Diego Rivera: His Life and Times (1939)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1951 (Folder 26: 1)
    - Libel suit, 1940-1942 (Folder 26: 2)
      Legal briefs, memoranda, correspondence and clippings.
    - Miscellany (Folder 26: 3)
    - Reviews, Printed copies. (Folder 26: 4)
    - Translation, Spanish
      - Preface, Typescript. (Folder 26: 5)
      - Printed copy (Folder 26: 6)
  - Keep America Out of War: A Program (with Norman Thomas, 1939), 1939-1967 (Folder 26: 7)
    Correspondence and reviews.
  - Review of Grace Lumpkin, The Wedding, 1939?; Printed copy (Folder 26: 8)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Laurence E. Schmeckebier, Modern Mexican Art, 1939?; Printed copy (Folder 26: 9)
  - "'Coordinating' Marxism," Workers Age, 1939 January 7; Printed copy (Folder 26: 10)
  - "Spain," speech, 1939 March 23; Handwritten notes (Folder 26: 11)
  - "War Against War-Makers!," speech, New York City, 1939 April 6; Printed copy (Folder 26: 12)
  - "Diego Rivera: People's Painter," radio broadcast, WEVD, New York City, 1939? May 23; Typescript (Folder 26: 13)
  - Report on Magdalena Mondragon, Yo Como Pobre (I, Being Poor), 1940s; Typescript (Folder 27: 1)
  - "Social Changes in the USSR,", 1940s; Typewritten prospectus (Folder 27: 2)
  - "What Next in the Orient?," speech, 1940s; Typescript (Folder 27: 3)
  - Translation of and introduction to Rosa Luxemburg, The Russian Revolution, pamphlet, 1940; Printed copy (Folder 27: 4)
  - World Without End: A Report on the Results of a Scientific Experiment, novel (1940)
    Chapters are in typescript unless otherwise noted.
    - Correspondence, typewritten notes, clipping, and contract, 1939-1940 (Folder 27: 5)
    - Prelude, Typescript and printed copy. (Folder 27: 6)
    - "Trying It on the Dog" (Folder 27: 7)
    - "From a Laboratory Tower" (Folder 27: 8)
    - "Tony Gets an Assignment" (Folder 27: 9)
    - "Doctor Calderon Reports" (Folder 27: 10)
    - "Calderon Gives an Interview" (Folder 27: 11)
    - "The City Celebrates" (Folder 27: 12)
    - "Aldrek Faces Eternity" (Folder 27: 13)
    - "The Stock Market Crashes" (Folder 27: 14)
    - "Ebb and Flow" (Folder 27: 15)
    - "Headlines" (Folder 27: 16)
    - "Beginning of the Great Schisms" (Folder 27: 17)
    - "The Song of Life" (Folder 27: 18)
    - "Mrs. Dowling's House Party" (Folder 27: 19)
    - "Death Gets the Upper Hand" (Folder 27: 20)
    - "The Last Broadcast" (Folder 27: 21)
    - Translation, Spanish, reviews, Printed copies. (Folder 27: 22)
  - "Oil and the Good Neighbor," Nation, 1940 April 27; Printed copy (Folder 27: 23)
  - Review in New Republic of Jan Valtin, Out of the Night, 1941 January 27; Printed copy (Folder 27: 24)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Mauritz A. Hallgren, Landscape of Freedom, 1941 February 16; Printed copy (Folder 27: 25)
  - Review in New Republic of Ella Reeve Bloor, We Are Many: An Autobiography, 1941 February 17; Printed copy (Folder 27: 26)
  - Review in New Republic of J. Fred Rippy, The Caribbean Danger Zone, William H. Haas, ed., The American Empire: A Symposium, Dwight C. Miner, The Fight for the Panama Route, and Carleton Beals, Panamerica: A Program for the Western Hemisphere, 1941 February 24; Printed copy (Folder 27: 27)
  - Review in Call (New York) of Manya Gordon, Workers Before and After Lenin, 1941 May 3; Printed copy (Folder 27: 28)
  - Review in New Republic of Edgcum Pinchon, Zapata the Unconquerable, 1941 May 19; Printed copy (Folder 27: 29)
  - "The Silent Soviet Revolution," Harpers Magazine, 1941 June (Folder 27: 30)
    Correspondence and printed copy.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of MacKinley Helm, Modern Mexican Painters, 1941 July 6; Printed copy (Folder 27: 31)
  - Review in New Republic of Lesley Byrd Simpson, Many Mexicos, and Virginia Prewett, Reportage on Mexico, 1941 September 1; Printed copy (Folder 27: 32)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Robert Redfield, The Folk Culture of Yucatan, 1941 October 5; Printed copy (Folder 27: 33)
  - Review in Russian Review of Maurice Hindus, Hitler Cannot Conquer Russia, 1941 November; Printed copy (Folder 27: 34)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Salvador de Madariaga, Hernan Cortes: Conqueror of Mexico, 1941 November 16; Printed copy (Folder 27: 35)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Gilbert Medioni and Marie-Therese Pinto, Art in Ancient Mexico, 1941 December 7; Printed copy (Folder 27: 36)
  - Review in New Leader of Betty Kirk, Covering the Mexican Front, 1942?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 1)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Robert S. Platt, Latin America: Countrysides and United Regions, 1942?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 2)
  - Review in Call (New York) of Anna Melissa Graves, ed., But the Twain Do Meet: Letters from the Near East, 1942 February 7; Printed copy (Folder 28: 3)
  - Review in New Republic of Lawrence Dame, Yucatan, Clifford Gessler, Pattern of Mexico, MacKinley Helm, Modern Mexican Painters, Robert Redfield, The Folk Culture of Yucatan, George C. Vaillant, Aztecs of Mexico, and Salvador de Madariaga, Hernan Cortes, 1942 February 9; Printed copy (Folder 28: 4)
  - Review in New Republic of Hugo Fernandez Artucio, The Nazi Underground in South America, 1942 April 27; Printed copy (Folder 28: 5)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Paul Miliukov, Outlines of Russian Culture, 1942 July 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 6)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Mary Heaton Vorse, Time and the Town: A Provincetown Chronicle, 1942 July 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 7)
  - "Advice We Can't Afford to Take," Progressive, 1942 July 25; Printed copy (Folder 28: 8)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Angel Flores and Dudley Poore, ed., Fiesta in November: Stories from Latin America, 1942 August 2; Printed copy (Folder 28: 9)
  - Review in Progressive of Klaus Mann, Andre Gide, 1942 August 30; Printed copy (Folder 28: 10)
  - "The Issue of the Rivera Murals: Good or Bad Art, True or False History?," New Leader, 1942 September 26; Printed copy (Folder 28: 11)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of A. Curtis Wilgus, ed., Hispanic American Essays, 1942 September 27; Printed copy (Folder 28: 12)
  - Review in New Republic of Paul Radin, Indians of South America, 1942 September 28; Printed copy (Folder 28: 13)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Watt Stewart and Harold F. Peterson, Builders of Latin America, 1942 November 8; Printed copy (Folder 28: 14)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Arturo Torres-Rioseco, The Epic of Latin American Literature, 1942 November 15; Typed copy (Folder 28: 15)
  - "Russia's New Religous Policy," Call (New York), 1942 December 4; Printed copy (Folder 28: 16)
  - Review in New Republic of Arturo Torres-Rioseco, The Epic of Latin American Literature, 1942 December 21; Printed copy (Folder 28: 17)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Salvador Dali, The Secret Life of Salvador Dali, 1942 December 27 (Folder 28: 18)
    Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence.
  - Review in Nation of Anita Brenner, The Wind that Swept Mexico, 1943?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 19)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of Harry A. Franck, Rediscovering South America, 1943?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 20)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of Waldo Frank, South American Journey, 1943?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 21)
  - Review of Albert B. Franklin, Ecuador, 1943?; Typescript (Folder 28: 22)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Luis Quintanilla, A Latin American Speaks, 1943 January 17; Printed copy (Folder 28: 23)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Erico Verissimo, Crossroads, 1943 January 31; Typed copy (Folder 28: 24)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Enrique Amorim, The Horse and His Shadow, 1943 February 8 (Folder 28: 25)
    Printed copy and correspondence.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Dudley Fitts, ed., Anthology of Contemporary Latin American Peotry, 1943 April 4; Printed copy (Folder 28: 26)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Benjamin Subercaseaux, Chile: A Geographic Extravaganza, 1943 April 18; Printed copy (Folder 28: 27)
  - "Stalin at the Peace Table," Common Sense, 1943 May; Printed copy (Folder 28: 28)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Earl Parker Hanson, ed., The New World Guides to the Latin American Republics, Vol. I: Mexico and Central America, 1943 May 16; Printed copy (Folder 28: 29)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Samuel Flagg Bemis, The Latin American Policy of the United States, 1943 May 23; Printed copy (Folder 28: 30)
  - Review in Progressive of Sidney Hook, The Hero in History, 1943 May 24; Printed copy (Folder 28: 31)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of Benjamin Subercaseaux, Chile: A Geographic Extravaganza, 1943 May 30; Printed copy (Folder 28: 32)
  - "Leon Felipe: Poet of Spain's Tragedy," American Scholar, 1943 Summer; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 28: 33)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of Anita Brenner, The Wind that Swept Mexico, 1943 June 13; Printed copy (Folder 28: 34)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of L. R. Dennison, Caroni Gold, 1943 June 20; Printed copy (Folder 28: 35)
  - Review in Progressive of John Dos Passos, Number One, 1943 July 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 36)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Enrique Gil Gilbert, Our Daily Bread, 1943 July 18; Printed copy (Folder 28: 37)
  - Review in Chicago Sun of Leland Dewitt Baldwin, The Story of the Americas, 1943 August 15; Printed copy (Folder 28: 38)
  - Review in New York Times of R. Palme Dutt, The Problem of India, and DeWitt Mackenzie, India's Problem Can Be Solved, 1943 September 5; Printed copy (Folder 28: 39)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of George Vernadsky, Ancient Russia, 1943 September 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 40)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of German Arciniegas, Germans in the Conquest of America, 1943 September 26; Printed copy (Folder 28: 41)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Earl Parker Hanson, ed., The New World Guides to the Latin American Republics, Vol. II: South America, 1943 October 10; Printed copy (Folder 28: 42)
  - Review in New Republic of Dudley Fitts, ed., An Anthology of Contemporary Latin American Poetry, 1943 October 11; Printed copy (Folder 28: 43)
  - Review in New York Times of William H. Prescott, The Conquest of Mexico, 1943 October 17 (Folder 28: 44)
  - Review in New York Times of William Henry Chamberlin, The Russian Enigma, 1943 October 31; Printed copy (Folder 28: 45)
  - Review in New York Times of Anna Louise Strong, Wild River, 1943 November 21; Printed copy (Folder 28: 46)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ciro Alegria, The Golden Serpent, 1943 December 12; Typed copy (Folder 28: 47)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of H. R. Hays, ed., American Poets: An Anthology, 1943? December 12; Typed copy (Folder 28: 48)
  - Review in New York Times of Salvador de Madariaga, Spain, 1943 December 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 49)
  - Lecture tour, 1944 (Folder 28: 50)
    Clippings and correspondence.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Cecilio Carneiro, The Bonfire, 1944?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 51)
  - Review in New Leader of David J. Dallin, The Real Soviet Russia, 1944? (Folder 28: 52)
    Printed copy, with comments by Benjamin Gitlow (typescript), notes for reply by Bertram D. Wolfe (holograph), and correspondence.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Hubert Herring, America and the Americas: An Appraisal and a Forecast, 1944?; Printed copy (Folder 28: 53)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Jefferson Rea Spell, Contemporary Spanish American Fiction, 1944; Printed copy (Folder 28: 54)
  - Review in New York Times of Gerhart H. Seger and Siegfried K. Marck, Germany: To be or Not To Be?, 1944 January 2; Printed copy (Folder 28: 55)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Mauricio Madgaleno, Sunburst, 1944 January 16; Printed copy (Folder 28: 56)
  - Review in New York Times of Louis Nizer, What to Do with Germany, 1944 January 30; Printed copy (Folder 28: 57)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Albert Parry, Russian Cavalcade, 1944 February 13; Printed copy (Folder 28: 58)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Foster Rhea Dulles, The Road to Teheran, 1944 February 27; Printed copy (Folder 28: 59)
  - Review in New York Times of Nicholson B. Adams, The Heritage of Spain, 1944 March 5; Printed copy (Folder 28: 60)
  - Review in New York Times of Vladimir I. Lenin: A Political Biography, 1944 March 5; Printed copy (Folder 28: 61)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ramon J. Sender, Chronicle of Dawn, 1944 March 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 62)
  - Review in New York Times of Walter Duranty, USSR: The Story of Soviet Russia, 1944 March 26 (Folder 28: 63)
    Printed copy, with printed copies of comment by Walter Duranty and reply by Bertram D. Wolfe (April 30).
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Salvador de Madariaga, The Heart of Jade, 1944 April 9; Printed copy (Folder 28: 64)
  - Letter to the editor, New Leader?, 1944 April 22; Printed copy (Folder 28: 65)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Joachim Joesten, What Russia Wants, 1944 May 7; Printed copy (Folder 28: 66)
  - Review in New York Times of Lewis Mumford, The Condition of Man, 1944 May 21; Printed copy (Folder 28: 67)
  - "Russia at the Peace Table," speech, American Friends Service Committee Institute of International Relations, Seattle, 1944 June 21; Printed copy (Folder 28: 68)
  - Review in New York Times of German Arciniegas, ed., The Green Continent: A Comprehensive View of Latin America by Its Leading Writers, 1944 August 20; Printed copy (Folder 28: 69)
  - "'Hire a Hall': Some Adventures on a Lecture Tour through the Land of Free Speech," New Leader, 1944 October 7; Printed copy (Folder 28: 70)
  - Review in New York Times of W. Rex Crawford, A Century of Latin-American Thought, 1944 October 8; Printed copy (Folder 28: 71)
  - Review in New York Times of Henry R. Wagner, The Rise of Fernando Cortes, 1944 October 8; Printed copy (Folder 28: 72)
  - "The Battle of San Francisco: Further Adventure on a Lecture Tour through the Land of Free Speech," New Leader, 1944 October 14 (Folder 28: 73)
  - Review in New York Times of Hudson Strode, Timeless Mexico, 1944 October 22; Printed copy (Folder 28: 74)
  - Review in New York Times of Kurt Severin, To the South, 1944 November 12; Printed copy (Folder 28: 75)
  - "Old and New Russia," speech, 1944 November 16; Typewritten notes (Folder 28: 76)
  - Review in New York Times of Jose Antonio de Aguirre, Escape via Berlin, 1944 November 19; Printed copy (Folder 28: 77)
  - Review in New Leader of Alexander Kaun, Soviet Poets and Poetry, 1944 December 2; Printed copy (Folder 28: 78)
  - Review in New York Times of William Henry Chamberlin, The Ukraine: A Submerged Nation, 1944 December 24 (Folder 28: 79)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Alfredo d'Escragnolle Taunay, Inocencia, 1945?; Printed copy (Folder 29: 1)
  - Review in New York Times of Edmund Stevens, Russia Is No Riddle, 1945?; Printed copy (Folder 29: 2)
  - "Should We Support Russia's Plans for Poland?," forum with Sir Bernard Pares, Albert Rhys Williams and Louis Fischer, Town Meeting of the Air broadcast, New York City, 1945 January 4; Printed transcript (Folder 29: 3)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of John and Mavis Biesanz, Costa Rican Life, 1945 January 14; Printed copy (Folder 29: 4)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Fighter for Workers Freedom," Call (New York), 1945 January 22; Printed copy (Folder 29: 5)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Frederick J. Pohl, Amerigo Vespucci, Pilot Major, 1945 January 28; Typed copy (Folder 29: 6)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Erico Verissimo, Brazilian Literature, 1945 February 11; Printed copy (Folder 29: 7)
  - "Poland: Acid Test of a People's Peace," Common Sense, 1945 March; Printed copy (Folder 29: 8)
  - Review in Progressive of William Henry Chamberlin, The Ukraine: A Submerged Nation, 1945 March 12; Printed copy (Folder 29: 9)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ricardo Rojas, San Martin: Knight of the Andes, 1945 April 22; Printed copy (Folder 29: 10)
  - Review in Common Sense of William L. White, Report on the Russians, and Edmund Stevens, Russia Is No Riddle, 1945 May; Printed copy (Folder 29: 11)
  - Review in New York Times of Gregory Bienstock, Solomon M. Schwarz and Aaron Yugow, Management in Russian Industry and Agriculture, 1945 May 13; Printed copy (Folder 29: 12)
  - Speech, rally to protest the arrest of sixteen Polish leaders, New York City, 1945 May 20; Typescript (Folder 29: 13)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Pedro Antonio de Alarcon, The Scandal, 1945 June 3; Printed copy (Folder 29: 14)
  - Review in New York Times of Pedro Henriquez-Urena, Literary Currents in Hispanic America, 1945 June 3; Typed copy (Folder 29: 15)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Jorge Amado, The Violent Land, 1945 June 17; Printed copy (Folder 29: 16)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Roland Hall Sharp, South America Uncensored, 1945 July 1; Printed copy (Folder 29: 17)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Carleton Beals, Bryce Oliver, Herschel Brickell and Samuel Guy Inman, What the South Americans Think of Us: A Symposium, 1945 July 8; Printed copy (Folder 29: 18)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Fritz Henle, Mexico, 1945 July 8; Printed copy (Folder 29: 19)
  - "Russia and the Peace," speech, Antioch College, Yellow Springs, Ohio, 1945 July 10; Handwritten and typewritten notes (Folder 29: 20)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ricardo Palma, The Knights of the Cape: Thrity-eight Selections from the Tradiciones Peruanas, 1945 August 5; Typed copy (Folder 29: 21)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Eleanor L. Turnbull, ed., Contemporary Spanish Poetry, 1945 August 26; Printed copy (Folder 29: 22)
  - "Lenin and the Agent Provocateur Malinovsky," Russian Review, 1945 Autumn; Printed copy (Folder 29: 23)